本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on the Bible...
犹太王国由伟大的英雄们一手建立
The Jewish nation has been forged in faith by great heroes.
以色列
Israel!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
亚巴郎证明了自己能成为万民之父
Abraham proved he was fit to father a nation.
梅瑟带领子民摆脱奴役  赢得了自由
Moses earned his people's freedom from slavery.
主啊
Lord!
达味攻下了耶路撒冷
David delivered the city of Jerusalem.
然而  以色列人的信念动摇了
But then... the Israelites' faith wavered.
国王成了暴君
Kings became tyrants.
腐败开始滋生
Corruption grew.
如今天主与子民之间的联系
Now the connection between God and his people
濒临崩溃
is at breaking point.
你崇拜的是异教的偶像
You worship foreign idols,
你玷污了你的天主
you defile your God!
去城门那儿
To the gates!
以色列人为之奋斗的一切
Everything the Israelites have fought for
受到了威胁
is under threat.
耶路撒冷的存亡掌握在一个软弱的新领袖手里
Jerusalem's survival depends on a weak new leader.
若 漆德克雅国王不归向天主  此城必亡
The city is doomed if King Zedekiah doesn't return to God.
射箭
Fire!
圣经
陛下
Your majesty.
耶路撒冷二十一岁的国王  漆德克雅
Jerusalem's 21st King - Zedekiah,
在两个超级大国之间 腹背受敌
is caught between the region's superpowers.
他与埃及勾结
He is conspiring with Egypt,
背弃了巴比伦
but owes allegiance to Babylon.
叛变的消息传到了
News of his betrayal has reached
巴比伦国王拿步高耳朵里
the Babylonian King Nebuchadnezzar.
拿步高  拿步高
Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar!
巴比伦
进攻  耶路撒冷
We move! Jerusalem!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
你知道耶路撒冷的含义吗
You know what it means, Jerusalem?
和平之城
City of Peace!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
自达味时期以来
Since the time of David,
耶肋米亚那样的先知们一直引导着他们的国王
prophets like Jeremiah have guided their kings.
他们是以色列和天主的直接联系
They are Israel's direct link with God.
但国王对耶肋米亚的警告置若罔闻
But Jeremiah's warnings have gone unheeded.
现在他要向漆德克雅传递最后的讯息
Now he delivers a final message to Zedekiah.
向拿步高投降
Surrender to Nebuchadnezzar...
否则就是死
Or die.
不忠的子民
Faithless people.
住手
No!
先知  那是什么
Prophet, what is that?
这就是你
This is you...
如果你足够明智
If you are wise,
就去臣服于巴比伦
place yourself under the yoke of Babylon -
接受主的惩罚
accept the Lord's retribution,
知道他仍对你宽容
and know that he is being lenient with you.
这是天主的旨意
These are God's words.
臣服于拿步高王
Submit to King Nebuchadnezzar.
向他低头
Bow your head.
你怎敢让王低头
You dare tell your king to bow down?
你怎敢质问天主的先知
How dare you question a prophet of God?
无礼的是你...
It is you who offends...
该认错的也是你
it's you who must change!
-把他带走  -叛徒
- Remove him. - Traitor!
天主将从巴比伦带来灾难
God is bringing disaster from Babylon.
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
去城门那儿
To the gates!
巴比伦人来了
The Babylonians!
快  进去
Quick, get inside!
-我的儿子  -父亲
- My son! - Father!
我的孩子
My son!
你来得太迟了
You are too late!
父亲
Father!
孩子
My son!
待在里面
Stay!
-父亲  -待在那儿
- Father! - Stay there.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
全城都封锁了吗
Is the city sealed?
是的  国王陛下
Yes, my king.
没人能逃脱
No one escapes.
战争开始了
It begins.
十八个月后  被围困的以色列人弹尽粮绝
After 18 months, the trapped Israelites start to starve.
绝望的百姓只能食人裹腹
The desperate resort to cannibalism.
滚开
Get off...
Get off!
弓箭手准备
Archers ready!
瞄准
Take aim.
射
Fire!
把火扑灭
Put the fire out!
"我与你们同在"
"I am with you"
上主如此说
...so saith the Lord.
先知
Prophet.
你不告知天主我们需要帮助吗
Will you not speak for us in our hour of need?
什么都没有变
Nothing has changed.
整个耶路撒冷将会被夷为平地
All Jerusalem will burn.
这是你写的
You wrote
"悔改吧  悔改吧
"Repent, repent,
"一切都会好起来  天主会拯救我们"
"And all will be well, God will save us."
看看外面
Look out there!
为时已晚
You're too late.
-现在  -就是现在
- Now! - Now!
再来  撞
And again! Push!
守住城门
Hold the gates!
撞
Push!
用力撞
Strike hard!
站到一起
Stand together!
用力撞  胜利是我们的
Strike hard and victory will be ours...
不管耶路撒冷还剩下什么
And whatever's left of Jerusalem...
随你们处置
...help yourselves!
别伤害我的孩子
Not my child.
在耶路撒冷被屠城之际
As Jerusalem is destroyed,
漆德克雅和他的儿子经由一条密道出逃
Zedekiah and his sons escape through a secret passageway.
现在要勇敢起来
Now you must be brave for me.
做得到吗
Can you do that?
别担心  我们会没事的
Don't worry, we'll be safe.
快  这边走
Quickly. This way.
他的子民就没这么幸运了
His people are not so lucky.
耶路撒冷是我们的
Jerusalem is ours...
Jerusalem is ours!
这是他们反抗我的惩罚
Punish them for trying to resist me...
让他们付出代价
Make them pay!
去圣殿
To the temple!
拿上所有东西
Take everything...
然后把这圣殿烧成平地
Then burn this temple to the ground.
圣殿  圣殿着火了
The temple! The temple's on fire!
我们为之奋斗的一切都没了
Everything we fought for is lost.
从亚巴郎时期开始
Since the time of Abraham,
犹太人为了盟约之地拼尽全力
the Jewish people have struggled for this promised land.
如今世世代代的希望和梦想
Now the hopes and dreams of generations
都化为乌有
are destroyed.
在逃亡求生的人当中
Among those fleeing for their lives--
有一个年轻的贵族叫达尼尔
a young nobleman called Daniel.
这边走  达尼尔
This way, Daniel.
帮帮我们  天主
Help us, Lord!
锁住了
It's locked!
达尼尔  躲到我身后
Daniel, get behind me.
等等
Wait!
这些人看上去有点用处
They look valuable.
活捉他们
Take them alive.
阿匝黎雅
Azariah...
不
No!
达尼尔  达尼尔
Daniel... Daniel!
阿匝黎雅
Azariah!
不  我们是天主的子民
No, we're people of God.
待在一起
Stay together.
阿匝黎雅
Azariah.
找到漆德克雅
Find Zedekiah.
找到他的家人
Find his family.
是  陛下
Yes, sir.
这就是背叛的代价
There's a price for betrayal.
别担心  孩子们  我们现在安全了
Don't worry, my boys. We're safe now.
漆德克雅
Zedekiah!
来  过来
Come, come here.
请...
Please...
放过他们
Leave them please...
天主啊
Dear God!
天主啊  不  请放过他们
Dear God, no! Leave them, please.
漆德克雅国王
King Zedekiah!
不  求你了  不
No! Please... Please, no.
求你了  天主
Please! Dear God.
天主  请放过他们
Dear God, spare them, please!
遗憾啊
A pity!
这便是你最后所见
The last thing you'll ever see.
带上他
Bring him.
犹太人被迫离乡背井
The Jewish people are forced into exile.
向东行走五百英里去往巴比伦
A 500 mile journey east to Babylon.
快走  快走
Move! Move!
漆德克雅是最后一个进行统治的达味王后裔
Zedekiah is the last of King David's descendants to reign.
快走
Move it!
以色列的君主制到此结束
The Israelite monarchy ends here.
耶肋米亚是成功逃生的极少数之一
Jeremiah is one of the few to escape.
他准备前往埃及  从此不再回来
He heads to Egypt never to return.
犹太人失去了他们的先知
The people have lost their prophet,
他们的城市
their city,
和他们的国王
and their king.
你  站起来
You there! On your feet!
好  举起来
All right, lift!
加油
Come on!
犹太民族需要一位不一样的领袖
The Jewish nation needs a different kind of leader
带领他们在巴比伦生存
to survive in Babylon.
一个像达尼尔这样的人
A man like Daniel.
巴比伦
达尼尔拥有预言的能力
Daniel has visionary powers
因此被迫在拿步高的宫廷里工作
and is forced to work in Nebuchadnezzar's court.
没人要告诉我什么吗
Has no one anything to tell me?
你们都描述不出我的梦吗
Can you not even describe my dream?
我要的不是沉默
Silence is no answer!
你们本应是"智者"
You're supposed to be 'wise men',
"巫师"  "占卜者"
'sorcerers', 'seers'...
你们看到了什么
So what do you see?
陛下
Sire...
请原谅我
Forgive me.
这里没有人能读懂你
No one here can read your mind...
那你们有何用处
Then what use are any of you?
但我的天主可以
But my God can.
他给我看了你的梦
He has shown me your dream.
那你就能告诉我
Then you will be able to tell it to me,
每一个细节
every detail.
你梦到一尊巨大的立像
You saw a giant statue of a man.
这尊立像，头是纯金的
Its head made of gold.
然后一块巨石撞向雕像
Then a giant stone struck the statue,
将它砸得粉碎
smashing it to pieces...
我知道这些
I know that much!
这意味着什么
What does it mean?
这座雕像代表着
The statue represents the empires
将臣服于巴比伦的国家
that will follow yours.
您的王国就是那黄金头像  傲视群雄
Yours is the greatest - the head of gold.
那破坏雕像的石块呢
And the stone that destroys the statue?
那是天主的国
That is the kingdom of God.
将来天主会君临世界
In the future God will reign over all the world...
直到永久
Forever.
被天主毁灭
Destroyed by God.
是的  陛下
Yes, sire.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
达尼尔
Daniel.
你是位勇士  达尼尔
You're a brave man, Daniel.
我欣赏这一点
I value that.
你会为我效力
You will serve me.
我们还会回到耶路撒冷吗
Will we ever return to Jerusalem?
耶肋米亚保证过...
Jeremiah promised that...
终有一天我们会的
that one day we would.
在那之前  我们要怎么做
And in the meantime, what do we do?
就对这个暴君俯首称臣吗
Just bow our heads and serve this monster?
我受不了了
I can't do it anymore.
想想我们的子民  阿匝黎雅
Think about our people, Azariah.
只要我们在宫廷内有了一席之地
As long as we're in the king's court,
我们就能帮助他们
we can help them.
如果我们坐牢或者死了  就帮不了他们了
Imprisoned or dead, we can't.
拿步高毁了天主的圣殿
Nebuchadnezzar destroyed God's Temple,
迫使我们流亡国外...
forced us into exile...
我的名字是阿匝黎雅
My name is Azariah,
意思是'受助于天主的人'
'He who is helped by God'...
现在我要祈求天主助我一臂之力
Well I call upon God to help me now!
如果你不跪拜他  他会杀了你的
He'll kill you if you won't bow.
我办不到
I can not.
我不会朝拜他的
I will not worship that.
开始
Now!
我们衷心追随你...
With all our hearts we follow you...
低头
Bow your heads!
我们寻求你的存在
We seek your presence...
我全心全意追随你
With all my heart I follow you.
敬畏你
I fear you.
寻求你的存在
I seek your presence.
抓住他们
Bring them!
我的朋友们
Oh my friends,
你们的信仰将会在此刻经受考验
your faith will be tested now.
达尼尔
Daniel!
他们是怎么回事
What's wrong with them?
为什么你的朋友们不愿叩拜于我
Why would your friends not bow to me?
陛下  我向您保证
I assure you, sire,
他们会像我一样
they will serve you faithfully
忠诚地侍奉您  但是...
all their lives, as I will, but...
但是
But?
但是他们将只信仰天主
But they will only worship God.
我会让他们臣服的
I will make them bow.
我们全心随从你，敬畏你，寻求你的慈颜
We follow you, we fear you, we seek your presence...
你们
You.
当我们想把坚硬稳固的东西弄弯时
When we wish to bend something that is hard and unyielding,
我们会怎么做
what do we do with it?
我们将它扔入火海
We put it into the fire.
陛下
Majesty...
把他带走
Take him.
我们敬畏你  我们寻求你的慈颜
We fear you, and we seek your presence.
烧死他们
Burn them!
陛下  不要
Majesty, no!
烧死他们  拿木材来
Burn them! Bring me wood...
把油拿来
Bring oil...
求你拯救我
Please save me!
点火
Fire...
给我点火
Bring me fire!
上主阿  求你俯听我的祈祷  留心听我的哀号
Hear my prayer, oh Lord. Hear my cry.
死亡的圈套缠住了我
The cords of death entangle me,
阴府的罗网缚住了我
the anguish of the grave consumes me.
请别忽视我的眼泪
Do not ignore my tears.
艰苦和烦恼困住了我
I'm overcome by sorrow.
我呼求上主的名
I call upon the name of the Lord...
主  救我
Lord save me...
天主俯听我的哀号
The Lord hears my cry.
天主听到我的祈祷
The Lord receives my prayer...
敌人将被威慑
My enemies will be daunted;
他们都将耻辱而回
they will turn back in shame.
为什么烧不死他们
Why do they not burn?
上主
Lord.
奇迹
It's a miracle.
犹太子民都起来吧
People of Judah, rise.
天主与我们同在
God is with us.
He's with us.
天主与我们同在
God is with us.
烈焰中的奇迹将犹太人紧密团结起来
The miracle in the fire unites the Jewish people.
在流亡中  他们对天主的信仰没有被削弱
Far from allowing their faith to weaken in exile,
反而更加坚定
they reaffirm their trust in God.
梅瑟在西乃山
The laws and histories
得到的《十诫》
that Moses received on Mount Sinai,
与《若苏厄书》  《撒慕尔记》
are preserved and compiled
和《列王记》一同被编纂保存下来
with the books of Joshua, Samuel and Kings.
(犹太教的启示性经典文献内容和旧约全书一致 但编排不同)
这几部分构成了《希伯来圣经》的核心
Together, they form the heart of the Hebrew Bible.
虽然犹太人有自己的信仰
The Jewish people have their faith,
但他们仍是阶下囚
but they're still prisoners.
唯一能释放他们的人
And the only man who can set them free
已经疯了
has lost his mind.
看看你如今的样子
So here you are...
拿步高
Nebuchadnezzar.
普天之下最伟大的国王和最低贱的子民
The greatest king and lowliest man on God's earth.
看看你的骄傲给你和我的同胞带来了
See where your pride has brought you?
怎样的下场
and us.
你本可以还我们自由
You could have set us free.
而现在  我们和你一样不得解脱
Now we are as trapped as you.
新王将立
A new king is coming.
祈求天主让他拯救我们
Please God, let him deliver us.
拿步高死后没几年
Within a few years of Nebuchadnezzar's death
一支庞大的军队来到巴比伦
a massive army approaches Babylon.
该军队由波斯王居鲁士领导
Led by Cyrus, king of Persia.
让他们知道我们来了
Let them know we've arrived.
巴比伦人知道自己没有胜算
The Babylonians know they don't stand a chance.
他们不战而降  将居鲁士迎入城内
They let Cyrus in without a fight.
居鲁士  居鲁士
Cyrus! Cyrus!
如果预言是正确的  那么居鲁士会释放我们
Cyrus will set us free if the prophecy is right.
为了保护他的犹太同胞
To protect his fellow Jews,
达尼尔与居鲁士亲近
Daniel befriends Cyrus
继续解梦
and continues to interpret dreams.
达尼尔  你的梦境意味着什么
But what does your dream mean, Daniel?
那不是我的梦  陛下
It's not my dream, sire.
曾经有一位先知名叫依撒意亚
There's a prophet here in Babylon - Isaiah -
他说  "有一位王  我牵着他的右手"
He says, "Here is a king whose right hand I take hold of"
"使他蹂躏他面前的列国"
"to subdue nations before him."
"他叫居鲁士"
"He is Cyrus."
他说的就是你  陛下
He names you, sire.
这意味着天主与你同在
It means God is with you.
你倒是会说话
I think you flatter me.
但从没有人会因会说话而丧命
But no one has ever died of flattery.
陛下立下众多丰功伟业
Your majesty has done many great things,
必将名垂青史
as the record will show.
理所应当
As it should.
我是居鲁士  万国之王
I am Cyrus, King of the world.
可他坚信达尼尔的每一句话
Yet he hangs on Daniel's every word
就像没有独立思考的能力一般
like he's lost the power to think for himself.
必须除掉达尼尔
Daniel must be removed.
一个月不准祷告
One month without prayer.
无疑只有叛徒才会反对
Surely only a traitor would object.
我不能言而无信
I cannot go back on my word.
我已承诺人民信仰自由
I promised them freedom to worship.
这只是考验他们的忠诚而已
It is merely a test of their loyalty.
他们已经历过那么多统治者
They've had so many rulers,
我们要确认他们将您视为最终的
we wanted to make sure they saw you as the final...
无与伦比的"万国之王"
ultimate "King of the World".
一个月不准祷告
One month without prayer...
也许居鲁士觉得这么做有意义
It probably sounds reasonable to Cyrus,
但他们知道我们不会照办的
but they know we can't comply.
他们压根不是为了波斯王
They don't care about the King,
不过是为了得到更大的权力罢了
they just want as much power over him as they can get.
所以要除掉你  免得你坏事
Which means they need you out of their way.
这是个圈套  他们想置我们于死地
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
一整个月  你要怎么做
A whole month. What will you do?
不知道
I don't know.
我只知道若不向天主祈祷  我命亦不会久
But I do know I can't live long without praying to God.
主啊  求你因你的名赐我救援
Save me, O God, by your name...
请怜悯我
Have mercy on me...
以永恒的慈爱
according to your unfailing love...
天主 求你给我再造一颗纯洁的心
create in me a pure heart, O God,
求你使我心重获坚固的精神
and renew a steadfast spirit within me...
求你不要从你的面前把我抛弃
Do not cast me from your presence
不要从我身上将你的圣神收回
or take your Holy Spirit from me,
求你使我重获你救恩的喜乐
but restore to me the joy of your salvation
求你以慷慨的精神来扶持我
and grant me a willing spirit, to sustain me.
达尼尔因为违抗居鲁士之令被捕
For disobeying Cyrus, Daniel is arrested
被判处死刑
and sentenced to death.
主啊  求你因你的名赐我救援
Save me, O God, by your name.
请怜悯我
Have mercy on me,
以你永恒的慈爱...
according to your unfailing love...
第二天早上
The next morning,
居鲁士意识到他犯了一个严重的错误
Cyrus realizes he's made a terrible mistake.
陛下  您身体不适吗
Sire, are you unwell?
我一晚上没睡着
I haven't slept.
天主  但愿我没来晚
Please God I'm not too late.
陛下  要我请医师来吗
Sire, should I call the physician?
我错待了我的朋友
I have wronged my friend.
开门
Open it!
达尼尔
Daniel?
天主与你同在
God is with you.
你的天主确实存在
Your God is real.
你的天主救了你
Your God has saved you.
是的
Yes.
我居鲁士  以万国之王之名下旨
I am Cyrus, King of the World, and my judgment is this:
你的人民可以回到耶路撒冷
your people shall return to Jerusalem.
他们的天主会很高兴
Their God will be pleased.
只可惜
Though, sadly...
他们没有可以敬拜主的圣殿
they no longer have a temple to worship him in.
把他扔进去喂狮子
Throw him in with the lions.
不  不
No... no...!
你知道这是什么吗
Do you know what this is?
是耶路撒冷圣殿里的器物
It's from the temple in Jerusalem.
真美
It's beautiful.
我从没见过有人用它
You know, I've never seen it used.
一直待在巴比伦  恐怕我也没机会用了
And staying here in Babylon, I suppose now I never will.
但我们的子孙可以
But our children will.
等他们重返耶路撒冷
When they get to Jerusalem.
等到圣殿重建  家国恢复之时
When the temple is re-built and the nation is restored...
我们的抗争就胜利了
our struggle is over.
我想给你看个东西
There's something I need to show you.
跟我来
Come with me.
看哪  我们的人民要回家了
Look, our people are heading home.
背井离乡数十载
After decades in exile,
他们依然团结一致  充满希望和信念
moving as one, with hope and purpose.
他们已经等得太久了
They've waited so long for this.
但我担心他们的未来
But I fear for their future.
我做了一个梦
I had a dream.
梦里我看到一只巨大的野兽
I saw a great beast,
面目狰狞  力大无穷
dreadful and terrible and unimaginably strong.
它有巨大的铁獠牙
It had great iron teeth,
吞噬了整个世界
and it devoured the whole world.
但天主不会弃我们而去
But God will not abandon us.
我在梦中还看见了一个伟大的新领袖
I saw a great new leader in my dream.
看见一位相似人子者
There before me was one, like a son of man,
乘着天上的云彩而来
coming with the clouds of heaven.
他便赐给似人子者统治权
He was given authority,
尊荣和国度
glory and sovereign power.
各民族 各邦国及各异语人民都要侍奉他
Nations and men of every language worshipped him.
这不是结局  阿匝黎雅
This isn't the end, Azariah...
而是开始
It's the beginning.
犹太人需要帮助
The Jewish people will need help
才能幸免于即将来临的灾难
to survive what is coming.
之后的五百年里
Over the next 500 years,
他们弱小的国家屡遭侵犯
Their tiny nation is attacked again and again.
接着他们臣服于罗马帝国的统治
Then they succumb to the might of Rome...
去排队
Get in line!
罗马的贪婪
Roman greed
前进
Forward!
罗马的法制
Roman law
罗马的惩罚
Roman punishment.
以色列遭受了前所未有的痛苦
Israel suffers like never before.
他们每天都在祈祷一位新达味王的降临
Every day, the people pray for a new King David
来拯救他们
to lead them to salvation.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on the Bible:
玛丽亚   我的未婚妻
Mary, my betrothed.
你有着我所见过最迷人的双眼
You have the most beautiful eyes I've ever seen,
和最甜美的笑容
and the sweetest smile.
我很好奇  您对新王都了解些什么
I wonder, what can you tell me of the new king?
你现在看到的黑落德王
Are you not looking at Herod,
难道不是犹太人的王吗
king of the Jews?
当然是
Of course.
那还有谁自称为王
Then who is claiming to be king?
现在还没有人  他还未出世
No one. He is not born yet.
这是一个预言  星相昭示了他的降临
It is a prophecy, heralded by the star.
杀了他们
Kill them.
把他们都杀死
Kill them all.
我扶着你
I've got you.
我为你们施洗
I baptize you,
准备迎接新的国度吧
ready for the new kingdom.
你已洁净
As you are cleansed...
所有以色列人也将和你一样洁净
... so all Israel shall be cleansed!
人们都去找这个野人一样的若翰
The people are flocking to this wild man, John.
有人甚至认为他就是默西亚
Some even call him the 'Messiah'.
那你可得好好留心这位默西亚了
Then you need to keep an eye on your 'Messiah'.
即将到来的那一位  大过我
There is one to come, greater than me,
他将用火来施洗
who will baptize with fire.
我不过是旷野中的声音  等待着主的...
I am just the voice in the wilderness, preparing the way for the...
...到来
...Lord.
他在这里
He's here.
就在这里
Out there.
开启人类的心智
Opening the hearts of all men.
凯撒的命令  异教活动必须停止
Orders from Caesar. This dissent must stop.
我们要做什么
What are we gonna do?
改变世界
Change the world.
他将带来正义与公平的新时代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice!
他的力量将带领人类迈向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world!
全人类
All people!
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!